welcome this is a short video to answer
the question that David sweat Lowe posed
to me on the recent Q&A and
unfortunately for a technological
problem technology is the God that limps
we were suddenly cast out of the techno
sphere and I'd like to now take this
opportunity to answer David's question
David's question again to remind
everyone is participatory knowing seems
the hardest lens to pull away and look
at rather than through but this seems
essential perhaps shamanic practices do
this thoughts are clarification on this
and I began by saying that I think this
is a really important question and also
the connection to shamanism is something
that we should talk about I went into
the idea of participatory knowing as
this mutual shaping between an organism
and its environment and I used Vic in
Stein's famous phrase enigmatic like
many things that the kitchen tine says
you know even if lions could speak we
wouldn't understand them and he means
you know utters syntactically correct
sentences etc and why is that well
here's the idea through what's called
niche constructions you know organisms
act in their environment and that shapes
and changes the environment which then
through natural selection shapes the
organism they mutually shape each other
so that they come to be fitted so that
affordances are generated between the
organism and the environment such that
an agent arena relationship is possible
so because of my evolutionary history I
am shaped with this kind of Dexter
dexterity and so this becomes you know
graspable and manipulative well by me in
a way that a dog can't do for example so
because of that biological niche
construction that biological mutual
shaping lines have a different form of
life within us so that coupling and the
set of affordances that it opens up of
course then skews the salience
landscaping of the prospective annoying
and their situational awareness is in
there in
in a fundamental sense very different
from mine so in that sense I don't know
what it's like to be a lion and that
means there that's so their perspective
on knowing is different and then that
means of course given that that that
shifting or skewing of their situational
awareness the skills they can acquire
and the skills they can apply are very
different from mine so their procedural
knowing is different and then if you
then were able to talk propositional you
know speech on top of that right I would
I couldn't make any sense of it because
that the sense of propositions would not
connect to my procedural knowing to my
prospective table knowing down to my
participatory in the knowing so even if
Lions could speak I wouldn't understand
them victims don't call this a form of
life now the point I want to make is
that of course we are different than
lions in that we don't just have
biological mutual shaping we have
cultural mutual shaping and that fact
that's what culture is culture is this
you know organization of distributed
cognition and meaning systems and
behavior such that the environment and
the and the agent are being mutually
shaped to each other so I I'm in a
particular culture in Canada and notice
the environment has been shaped around
me this way and I'm shaped in certain
ways both in my behavior the clothing I
wear etc so culture is also this mutual
shaping that creates all kinds of
affordances that's why you when you go
to a culture that is foreign to you you
experience culture shock not because you
don't have you know sort of biological
fitness to the environment but because
that mutual shaping between you and the
environment that is done by culture is
not available to you so you can lock
that kind of participatory knowing and
then of course on top of that you have
cognitive mutual shaping in which you
know your relevance realization
machinery
you know below the level of your ego
awareness is shaping your processing and
it's a specializing the environment so
that it fits to you so things come up to
you in the moment
cognitively so and I've course I'm
presenting these analytically and within
and that's for purposes of understanding
but of course the biological the
cultural and the cognitive are all right
right
mutually interpenetrating and affording
each other and I try to when I talk
about participatory knowing I'm talking
about invoking all of that now what's
interesting about shamanism is I think
shamanism and this is I think why David
brought it up shamanism is very much an
attempt
sorry attempt sounds too weak it's very
much a practice that what it's doing is
this of course because of the and this
goes back to a question I answer the Q&A
about mimesis because the shaman for
example is right in acting the dear the
shaman is trying to use his or her
altered state of consciousness which has
loosened up their salience landscape so
that they can get closer to what it's
like to see things to the way a deer
does to salience landscape the way a
deer does and then what they're doing is
they're actually trying to move their
body and you know
a-a-a and enact it through sort of an
inactive transformation even get down to
sort of transforming a bit the
biological niche construction what what
kind of body and that's why you wear the
mask and they sort of hunker down and
move in certain ways so what did what
you're trying to do is the shaman is
trying to alter consciousness trying to
alter sort their their their their
biological their biology in terms of
their behavior and even there's sort of
a morphology and of course trying to you
know pick up on certain skills that the
deer might have and I think what those
practices do is they really do give you
a sense of participatory knowing insofar
as you can move between them if you'll
allow me world to mean agent arena cocoa
configuration right as the shaman moves
between the human world
and the sacred world of the animals for
example that a capacity to move between
them is going to bring to awareness as
David said the normally transparent lens
of our participatory knowing it's really
interesting that how this comes up I
gave a talk recently a ute ism about and
I've mentioned this before about you
know with the scientists working with
the Rovers on Mars and you can see them
sort of having to create this nice
construction they said they
anthropomorphize the rover and they sort
of techni morph eyes themselves like for
safety talk talks about so they'll talk
about the rover to say like I or we need
to go there but they'll also say you
know they'll enact being the rover they
put their hands up like camera like this
and they move a rep how I need to turn
right and so they they do this mutual
shaping because they also shape the the
photos that they're getting they draw on
them and they they alter the Stallions
patterns so they shape themselves and
they sort of specialize and identify
with the rover and they shape the photos
that the rover sending back because
they're trying to create that
participatory knowing so they get a
sense of being on Mars because when they
can get that sense of being on Mars then
they can do the best fieldwork on Mars
they can train and apply the best set of
skills so it's you can see rocket
scientists behaving in ways that are
kind of like the shamans they'll say
things like you know I was working in my
garden in my right hand got stuck and
when I got to the lab the Rovers right
front wheel with stock and you know I
don't believe in magic but there's some
kind of connection you know that it
sounds very much like they're exacting
that shamanic machinery with it I think
we do have not Rossano argues for this
in Supernatural selection that we
probably shamanism has probably been
around since the Upper Paleolithic
transition and was a set of psycho tips
a psycho technological practices that
exalted our capacity for altering our
state of consciousness
of respectable and our participatory
knowing as I've just described and that
that's been around long enough and it
there might have been been something
like a Baldwin effect that those
individuals would enhance the group that
they belong to surviving much more
likely for those kinds of integrals will
be to reproduce etc and that sort of we
might be genetically disposed towards
shamanism this is one explanation why we
seem to have something like the placebo
effect why we seem to be hypnotizable
things like that so I think what I'm
suggesting to you is we have these
capacities from our shamanic
heritage if you'll allow me that turn of
phrase that can get exact it even by the
scientists who are doing this having to
confront this very new and bizarre way
of doing their science and so that shows
me that I think there is something I
think David's question is really sort of
powerful on how it points to the way
shamanism gives us access to becoming
aware much more better more aware of our
participatory knowing and yet
nevertheless how you can see it
spontaneously come or something at least
that's been exempted in an analogous
fashion you can see it in the work of
sort of literal cutting the you know
cutting edge literal rocket scientists
working with some of our hyper
technology on Mars and and so I think
that's a really great question and
glad I got this opportunity if you
answer it more fully so thank you David
very much for it and thank thank you for
those who tuned in to my Q&A we got cut
off before I could thank you all thank
you all so very much
and thank you for watching this video as
well take care everyone thank you for
your time and attention